<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>hugo-site on Bas Machielsen</title>
    <link>/tags/hugo-site/</link>
    <description>Recent content in hugo-site on Bas Machielsen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/hugo-site/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>MSc Thesis Economic Policy</title>
      <link>/project/hist_pers_2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/hist_pers_2023/</guid>
      <description> Introduction The link above contains:
The lecture slides for an introduction session for the applied economics research course can be found here: </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MSc Thesis Economic Policy</title>
      <link>/project/thesis2023ep/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/thesis2023ep/</guid>
      <description> Introduction The link above contains:
The lecture slides for an introduction session for thesis supervision for the MSc program in Economic Policy (2022-2023 academic year) </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD Thesis</title>
      <link>/articles/phd_thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/articles/phd_thesis/</guid>
      <description>My PhD Thesis My PhD Thesis is available in two parts. First, the actual thesis, which is downloadable via this link.
Replication Package The main thesis is accompanied by a replication package, which can be found here. The purpose of this package is to share shareable data, but also to make my findings reproducible by showing the code that lead to the results in each table.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Returns to Politics Under A Changing Political System</title>
      <link>/articles/polrents/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/articles/polrents/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Economists frequently assert that politicians derive financial returns from a political career, but it is unclear what allows them to do so. In this paper, I derive estimates of the returns to consecutive Lower House mandates exploiting the repeated treatment assignment resulting from Dutch district-level elections (1860-1917). Based on newly-collected data from probate inventories, I obtain a measure of personal wealth for a sample of just-elected politicians and their losing contenders.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis Supervision 2022</title>
      <link>/project/thesis2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/thesis2022/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Democratization, Personal Wealth of Politicians and Voting Behavior</title>
      <link>/articles/polelite_vb/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/articles/polelite_vb/</guid>
      <description>Abstract From about 1850 to 1920, a wave of democratization and liberalization swept over Western Europe, bringing about universal suffrage and an expansion of government. Using newly-collected probate inventories that provide a measure of politicians&amp;rsquo; personal wealth, this paper investigates the role of personal wealth in this process illustrated by the case of the Netherlands. I show that parliaments became significantly less wealthy over time. I then analyze voting behavior of politicians on several laws extending the franchise and increasing taxes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Wealth of The Dutch Political Elite (1870-1922)</title>
      <link>/articles/wealth/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/articles/wealth/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Using newly-collected archival data, this study investigates the wealth and investment portfolio&amp;rsquo;s of Dutch politicians from 1870 to 1922. In a period when the political and economic situation underwent many changes, this study finds that the political arena remains rather static: politicians are wealthy in comparison to the average citizen. Secondly, Upper House members are by far the wealthiest politicians followed by executives. Lower house politicians are the poorest on average, consistent with the lower house being accessible by the entire male population of the country.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BSc Theses Political Connections</title>
      <link>/project/polcon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/polcon/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In short, this theme will allow you to:
Get to know the main literature about political connections. Understand the main theories about political connections and political interference with business and markets. Understand the difference between empirical and theoretical questions, and identify the main methods used in empirical research. Formulate your own ideas about political connections Get an impression of the variation of mechanisms around the world to regulate politicians&amp;rsquo; behavior.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis Supervision 2021</title>
      <link>/project/thesis2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/thesis2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Big Data, Big Questions</title>
      <link>/project/bdbq/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/bdbq/</guid>
      <description>Introduction The links above contain:
A repository for my course materials used in the working groups for the course Big Data, Big Questions at Utrecht University.
This includes data sources, lecture slides, and other resources The lecture slides</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
