<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bas Machielsen</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Bas Machielsen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>cbs_hist_downloader</title>
      <link>/collection/cbs_hist_downloader/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/collection/cbs_hist_downloader/</guid>
      <description>CBS Historisch contains digitalized images of various books, serving as useful data sources. The website is quite slow and tedious to use. This Python-based tools allows users to download the images to their hard drives and inspect/read them there. It is also available on PyPI here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clio</title>
      <link>/collection/clio/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/collection/clio/</guid>
      <description>Clio is an R package that serves as a bridge between the user and the website Clio Infra, a repository containing publicly available data on various aspects of economic history at the country level. This package is designed to quickly and efficiently extract data, allowing the user to make large queries. This way, the user is not confined to manually downloading Excel files, and the associated filtering and merging process. The package also facilitates transparent and reproducible data collection, and it is ‘typo robust’ to a certain extent, to prevent annoyance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>HDNG</title>
      <link>/collection/hdng/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/collection/hdng/</guid>
      <description>hdng is a package facilitating the use of the HDNG Database, a database containing quantative information in various aspects of Dutch municipalities from about 1800 to the 1980&amp;rsquo;s. This package aids the user in finding their way through the database, allowing them to search for wanted variables, browse within categories, and finally, make a query to extract the wanted data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Polars Selectors</title>
      <link>/blog/2025-07-08-polars-selectors/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2025-07-08-polars-selectors/</guid>
      <description>Excellent. Let&amp;rsquo;s dive into these more advanced and idiomatic Polars techniques. These patterns are crucial for writing concise, expressive, and efficient Polars code, moving beyond basic transformations into more nuanced data manipulation.
We will use a new example dataset for these concepts to better illustrate their specific use cases. Let&amp;rsquo;s imagine a dataset from a university&amp;rsquo;s course enrollment system.
import polars as pl import polars.selectors as cs # We&amp;#39;ll need this for advanced column selection # Create our example DataFrame df_courses = pl.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Python Polars Demonstration for Data Wrangling</title>
      <link>/blog/2025-07-08-python-polars-demonstration-for-data-wrangling/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2025-07-08-python-polars-demonstration-for-data-wrangling/</guid>
      <description>Introduction I’ve never really liked pandas. I always thought it was tedious to work with and it bothered me there were never really quick ways to do something simple. Thinks like renaming, filtering and selecting columns were always more tedious than they should’ve been too. Since a while now, I’ve been using the Python library polars instead. polars has an API which is much more similar to the R tidyverse system, it’s super suitable for piped sequences of code, and it has a submodule called polars.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Random Effects Regression: A Mathematical Exposition</title>
      <link>/blog/2025-05-23-random-effects-regression-a-mathematical-exposition/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2025-05-23-random-effects-regression-a-mathematical-exposition/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Hi all, I wanted to write a short primer on random effects regression, since I&amp;rsquo;m working on this for a course I&amp;rsquo;m teaching, and I think the exposition in most textbooks isn&amp;rsquo;t that clear. To improve this, I present a mathematical derivation of the random effects model here. I should note that I&amp;rsquo;m not a fan of the random effects model at all. I think it should be seen as a curiosity rather than a solution in many cases.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Geospatial Interpolation: Some Theory</title>
      <link>/blog/2024-12-05-geospatial-interpolation-some-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2024-12-05-geospatial-interpolation-some-theory/</guid>
      <description>1. Introduction Hi all, I want to write about geospatial interpolation methods and the underlying math. Potentially, in a follow-up blog post, I&amp;rsquo;ll also discuss example, but in this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll confine myself to some of the theory, introducing concepts like the variogram and the kriging equations: terms which I wasn&amp;rsquo;t familiar with until very recently. So this post serves as a consolidation of my newly obtained knowledge. It can serve as a background to a text such as this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Short Memo About Inverse Probability Weighting</title>
      <link>/blog/2024-11-30-short-memo-about-inverse-probability-weighting/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2024-11-30-short-memo-about-inverse-probability-weighting/</guid>
      <description>Introduction I want to briefly have on paper the logic behind using inverse probability-weighted estimators of the ATT (average treatment effect on the treated) in a causal inference context.
Setup Let \(Y(1)\) and \(Y(0)\) denote the potential outcomes under treatment and no treatment, respectively.
The ATT is defined as:
$$ ATT=\mathbb{E}[Y(1)−Y(0)∣T=1] $$
where \(T \in \{0,1\}\) indicates treatment status.
We assume that conditional on covariates \(X\), the treatment is independent of \(Y(0)\), an assumption known as unconfoundedness.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Applied Data Science</title>
      <link>/project/iads/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/iads/</guid>
      <description> Introduction The link above contains the lecture slides for three sessions on the theme &amp;ldquo;Historical Persistence&amp;rdquo; for the Applied Economics Research Course, a 3rd year BSc-level course. The lectures are as follows:
Lecture 1: Introduction to Data Science &amp;amp; R Lecture 2: Introduction to Programming Lecture 3: Getting Data, API &amp;amp; Databases Lecture 4: Getting Data, Web Scraping Lecture 5: Transforming and Cleaning Data Lecture 6: Spatial and Network Data Lecture 7: Text Data &amp;amp; Text Mining Lecture 8: Applied Data Science Project </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sampling Variation in Linear Regression</title>
      <link>/blog/2024-10-07-sampling-variation-in-linear-regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2024-10-07-sampling-variation-in-linear-regression/</guid>
      <description>Sampling Variation and Regression Analysis Introduction This blog post on sampling variation in regression analysis is part two of a two-part blog post on sample variations. In part 1, available here, I provide a gentle introduction to the subject and present the logic of hypothesis testing. In this part, I derive the sampling distribution for the \(\beta\) coefficients in a standard linear regression model. Some of the derivations here are technical, but those can be skipped by the reader not interested in petty details.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is Sampling Variation?</title>
      <link>/blog/2024-10-07-what-is-sampling-variation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2024-10-07-what-is-sampling-variation/</guid>
      <description>What is Sampling Variation? Introduction In this blog post, I want to pay attention to the concept of sampling variation. In my econometrics classes, I have often found that students have a hard time wrapping their heads around this concept, especially in the case of regression analysis. Some of the questions I often get range from &amp;ldquo;why is our estimate of \(\beta\) uncertain, since we have obtained it in a deterministic way from our data sample&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;where do \(t\) statistics come from?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intervals and Durations in Feeding a New-born :)</title>
      <link>/blog/2024-06-02-intervals-and-durations-in-feeding-a-new-born/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2024-06-02-intervals-and-durations-in-feeding-a-new-born/</guid>
      <description>Introduction As those of you who might know me know, we (my wife and me) became parents a couple of months ago of a son named Lev. Apart from being a really cool guy, he’s also quite unpredictable in his tendencies for asking to be fed. We’ve been using an app called Huckleberry to record all feeding times and duration, and since he can be quite demanding, we were wondering about the relationship between feeding duration and times (intervals) between feeding.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to create a running variable in a spatial RDD?</title>
      <link>/blog/2024-05-14-how-to-create-a-running-variable-in-a-spatial-rdd/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2024-05-14-how-to-create-a-running-variable-in-a-spatial-rdd/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll explain, using R code, how to create a distance to the border and an associated running variable often met in geographic regression discontinuity designs. Depending on your data, this can be kind of difficult, so I&amp;rsquo;ll explain this using two examples:
One using raster data, computing distance to the border of the Roman Empire, inspired by a teaching project One using vector data, computing distance to the Veneto-Lombardo border, inspired by a research project with Giacomo Domini.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Returns to Political Tenure</title>
      <link>/articles/polrents/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/articles/polrents/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Economists frequently assert that politicians derive financial returns from a political career, but these returns can be obscured by the varying duration of political careers. In this study, I estimate the financial returns associated with successive mandates in the Lower House, capitalizing on the repetitive treatment assignment through close elections in the Netherlands from 1848-1917. Employing a dynamic regression discontinuity framework, I establish that the financial benefits accruing to politicians exhibit a distinct &amp;ldquo;gate-keeping&amp;rdquo; pattern: no financial gains are observed during the first period of political tenure, but substantial returns emerge during the second term.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trends in Fertility Rates Worldwide and in Europe</title>
      <link>/blog/2024-01-04-trends-in-fertility-rates-worldwide-and-in-europe/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2024-01-04-trends-in-fertility-rates-worldwide-and-in-europe/</guid>
      <description>Introduction After some discussions I&amp;rsquo;ve had with people, I thought it&amp;rsquo;d be interesting to look at the data to see what trends in fertility rates are visible in a cross-country context. By now, I guess it is well-known that some countries, notably South-Korea and Japan, but also other East Asian countries as well as European countries have been stuck in a very low fertility rate regime (a TFR of about 1, or just slightly higher) for some time, creating demographic problems such as an &amp;ldquo;inverse population pyramid&amp;rdquo; which can in turn entail manifold economic costs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spectral Clustering Polygons into Macroregions</title>
      <link>/blog/2023-10-21-spectral-clustering-polygons-into-macroregions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2023-10-21-spectral-clustering-polygons-into-macroregions/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this blog post, I want to show how to use spectral clustering, an unsupervised machine learning algorithm, to cluster polygons into macroregions. An application of this method of clustering might be to aggregate from the city/municipality level up to a higher level, but not the province level (which is something likely to already be in your shapefile). This gives a researcher the opportunity to combine observations from different, but geographically close cities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Performance of Probabilistic Latent Semantic Analysis</title>
      <link>/blog/2023-10-05-the-performance-of-probabilistic-latent-semantic-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2023-10-05-the-performance-of-probabilistic-latent-semantic-analysis/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this blog post, I want to investigate the performance of probabilistic latent semantic analysis: a subject I have been teaching (but also studying) for a course. Probabilistic latent semantic analysis proceeds from a document-term matrix, a standard data matrix in the field of text mining. It should look something like this, where the rows of the matrix represent \(n\) documents and the columns \(p\) terms (words). Usually, \(p &amp;gt; n\).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Democratization, Personal Wealth of Politicians and Voting Behavior</title>
      <link>/articles/polelite_vb/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/articles/polelite_vb/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Between about 1850 and 1920, Western Europe underwent a period of democratization and liberalization, resulting in the expansion of government and the establishment of universal suffrage. This paper examines the impact of politicians&amp;rsquo; personal wealth on this process, with a focus on the case of the Netherlands, using data from newly-collected probate inventories as a measure of politicians&amp;rsquo; wealth. The paper finds that the wealth of parliaments decreased significantly over time, and that richer politicians were more likely to vote against fiscal legislation, suggesting that personal wealth negatively influenced the probability of increasing taxes and played a role in determining government size.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inference with Raster Spatial Data in R</title>
      <link>/blog/2023-05-04-inference-with-raster-spatial-data-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2023-05-04-inference-with-raster-spatial-data-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this blog post, I want to demonstrate how to work with spatial raster data in R. I already have a couple of tutorials on vector data, but in this blog post, I want to focus exclusively on raster data. I&amp;rsquo;ll be replicating a paper about Roman Roads by Dalgaard et al. (2021), which attempts to identify the persistent influence of Roman roads (built in the Roman empire) on later economic development.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Historical Persistence</title>
      <link>/project/hist_pers_2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/hist_pers_2023/</guid>
      <description> Introduction The link above contains the lecture slides for three sessions on the theme “Historical Persistence” for the Applied Economics Research Course, a 3rd year BSc-level course. The lectures are as follows:
Lecture 1: Historical Persistence and an Introduction to Geospatial Data Lecture 2: Manipulating and Aggregating Vector and Raster Data Lecture 3: Geographic Regression Discontinuity Designs Lecture 4: Additional Data Wrangling Example Presentation </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Democracy and peace</title>
      <link>/blog/2023-02-27-democracy-and-peace/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2023-02-27-democracy-and-peace/</guid>
      <description>Introduction I wanted to write a short post on democratic peace theory to simply explore the correlation between democracy and peace. It is sometimes believed that democratic countries are less likely to wage war on each other than autocratic countries, and furthermore, that democratic countries are less likely to wage war in general (either against autocratic or democratic countries). In this blog post, I want to explore the data to see to which extent this holds true.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial Merging Roman Roads with Eurostat Data</title>
      <link>/blog/2023-02-15-spatial-merging-roman-roads-with-eurostat-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2023-02-15-spatial-merging-roman-roads-with-eurostat-data/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this short blog post, I focus on combining several European municipal (LAU, Local Urban Areas) shapefiles, combined with data on roads and cities in the Roman Empire, to find relationships between present-day outcomes and deep-routed interventions as far as more than 2000 years ago.
Let us first load the libraries we need to perform operations.
library(tidyverse) library(giscoR) library(sf) library(cawd) library(regions) For robustness, and out of curiosity, I will use two roads files.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial Operations in R</title>
      <link>/blog/2023-02-15-spatial-operations-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2023-02-15-spatial-operations-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this post, I will demonstrate some useful spatial operations in R. In particular, I want to do some spatial data wrangling to generate a border between two areas on a particular map, and afterwards, compute the distance of each polygon (area) to that border. This is something that is often featured in spatial regression discontinuity designs, where the &amp;ldquo;running&amp;rdquo; variable is the distance (positive or negative) from the border, the border being, for example, ancient borders, an area of exploitation, some territory impacted by some event, or some seized territory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Radio broadcast about my PhD Thesis</title>
      <link>/blog/2023-01-20-radio-broadcast-about-my-phd-thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2023-01-20-radio-broadcast-about-my-phd-thesis/</guid>
      <description>Radio Broadcast I was invited to the Dutch radio program Spraakmakers to talk about my PhD thesis. You can listen to the recording here. The part where I show up is roughly from 1:11:25 to 1:27:00. I am discussing with political historian Remieg Aerts and presenter Carl-Johan de Zwart about the Dutch political system in the 19th century in light of the findings in my PhD dissertation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Overview of Economics Datasets and Databases</title>
      <link>/blog/2022-12-06-overview-of-economic-history-datasets-and-databases/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2022-12-06-overview-of-economic-history-datasets-and-databases/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll give an overview and short description of various commonly-used and mostly publicly available data sources in Economic History. I am planning to update this repository as soon as I find new data sources, so if you find something is missing or if you have any suggestions, please contact me or write a comment below! Thanks to Giacomo Domini and Ruben Peeters for suggesting several of these sources.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MSc Thesis Economic Policy</title>
      <link>/project/thesis2023ep/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/thesis2023ep/</guid>
      <description> Introduction The link above contains:
The lecture slides for an introduction session for thesis supervision for the MSc program in Economic Policy (2022-2023 academic year) </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Short Note on Ridge Regression</title>
      <link>/blog/2022-11-23-short-note-on-ridge-regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2022-11-23-short-note-on-ridge-regression/</guid>
      <description>Introduction I am doing a couple of assignments involving penalized estimators such as Ridge regression, and I wanted to do a short derivation of its asymptotic covariance. In comparison to the existing resources which I could find, some details are left out, which I wanted to recapitulate more clearly. I&amp;rsquo;ll also contrast the variance of the Ridge estimator to the variance of the OLS estimator, illustrating a fact that also comes to the surface in many other resources, namely that the variance of the Ridge estimator is smaller than that of the OLS estimator.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-Negative Matrix Factorization</title>
      <link>/blog/2022-10-05-non-negative-matrix-factorization/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2022-10-05-non-negative-matrix-factorization/</guid>
      <description>Introduction For a course I am teaching in, the syllabus includes an alternative to Principal Component Analysis, called non-negative matrix factorization. The method was introduced in an article by Lee and Seung (1999) with a subsequent elaboration on the algorithm to implement the method in 2001. The method is described in the Elements of Statistical Learning, p. 553, but there is very little elaboration on the meaning and logic behind the updating rule.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Equilibria in Several Interesting Games</title>
      <link>/blog/2022-08-08-bayesian-equilibria-in-several-interesting-games/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2022-08-08-bayesian-equilibria-in-several-interesting-games/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this post, I want to work out a couple of games using the concept of Bayesian Nash Equilibria. Bayesian Nash Equilibria are a kind of intermediate step between basic Nash equilibria and Perfect Bayesian Equilibria, which involve multiple stages and require beliefs consistent with Bayes Rules on the equilibrium path.
Bayesian Nash Equilibria are somewhat simpler, and usually involve only one action per type realization, and best responses based on the distribution of type realization of the other players (again conditional on one&amp;rsquo;s own type realization).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD Thesis</title>
      <link>/articles/phd_thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/articles/phd_thesis/</guid>
      <description>My PhD Thesis My PhD Thesis is available in two parts. First, the actual thesis, which is downloadable via this link.
Replication Package The main thesis is accompanied by a replication package, which can be found here. The purpose of this package is to share shareable data, but also to make my findings reproducible by showing the code that lead to the results in each table.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis Supervision 2022</title>
      <link>/project/thesis2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/thesis2022/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A computational implementation of the Besley (2004) model</title>
      <link>/blog/2022-08-09-a-computational-implementation-of-the-besley-2004-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2022-08-09-a-computational-implementation-of-the-besley-2004-model/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Besley (2004) is a paper about the effects of politicians&amp;rsquo; pay (e.g. wages) on performance. This is a classic issue, tackled firstly by Barro (1973) and Ferejohn (1986), but only recently, the literature has looked into issues surrounding the effect of wages on selection. In the literature, there is a debate about whether higher wages attract better-quality individuals or lesser-quality individuals to the political arena. Besley (2004) is a paper rationalizing the first view.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Equilibrium in the Besley-Case (1995) Model</title>
      <link>/blog/2022-08-03-equilibrium-in-the-besley-case-1995-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2022-08-03-equilibrium-in-the-besley-case-1995-model/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Besley and Case (1995) have a paper about the influence of term limits for politicians on policy behavior. They use a dynamic game. Politicians can serve either 1, or 2, periods, depending on whether they are retained. In these periods, politicians choose to put in effort. Putting in more or less effort is costly to different extents, according to their type. The chosen effort probabilistically affects a policy outcome.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Podcast (Dutch) about my PhD Projects</title>
      <link>/blog/2022-08-03-podcast-dutch-about-my-phd-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2022-08-03-podcast-dutch-about-my-phd-projects/</guid>
      <description>Introduction I was interviewed by the Dutch economics journal Economisch-Statistische Berichten (ESB) about my PhD work as a part of their new Podcast series on New Economists. In the podcast, I talk about the influence of politicians&amp;rsquo; personal wealth interests on their voting behavior and the many consequences this might have. I also dive into history and give some tangible examples when politicians&amp;rsquo; personal wealth might play a role, and when it might not.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Wealth of The Dutch Political Elite (1870-1922)</title>
      <link>/articles/wealth/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/articles/wealth/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Using newly-collected archival data, this study investigates the wealth and investment portfolio&amp;rsquo;s of Dutch politicians from 1870 to 1922. In a period when the political and economic situation underwent many changes, this study finds that the political arena remains rather static: politicians are wealthy in comparison to the average citizen. Secondly, Upper House members are by far the wealthiest politicians followed by executives. Lower house politicians are the poorest on average, consistent with the lower house being accessible by the entire male population of the country.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BSc Theses Political Connections</title>
      <link>/project/polcon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/polcon/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In short, this theme will allow you to:
Get to know the main literature about political connections. Understand the main theories about political connections and political interference with business and markets. Understand the difference between empirical and theoretical questions, and identify the main methods used in empirical research. Formulate your own ideas about political connections Get an impression of the variation of mechanisms around the world to regulate politicians&amp;rsquo; behavior.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thesis Supervision 2021</title>
      <link>/project/thesis2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/thesis2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A From-Scratch Implementation of Neural Networks in Python</title>
      <link>/blog/2022-08-03-a-from-scratch-implementation-of-neural-networks-in-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2022-08-03-a-from-scratch-implementation-of-neural-networks-in-python/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this blog post, I wanted to write down an easy implementation of neural networks in Python. The model architecture of neural networks contains three pillars:
The actual model (Multi-layer perceptron network), with inputs, layers, and outputs, and weights connecting these. Forward propagation - the loop from inputs to subsequent layers and finally, the output, using given weights. Backward propagation - updating the weights with gradient descent to minimize the loss.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Mathematics Underlying Deep Learning</title>
      <link>/blog/2022-08-03-the-mathematics-underlying-deep-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2022-08-03-the-mathematics-underlying-deep-learning/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this post, I want to provide a quick primer about the mathematics underlying the backpropagation algorithm in neural networks and deep learning algorithms. I use the notation provided in this book, chapter 2, and prove/explain in-depth where some of the equations come from. I hope this provides an intuitive and clear explanation about the logic underlying backpropagation, and it should make it easy to implement this using code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A few game theory exercises and answers</title>
      <link>/blog/2022-08-03-a-few-game-theory-exercises-and-answers/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2022-08-03-a-few-game-theory-exercises-and-answers/</guid>
      <description>Introduction I want to work out a couple of exercises from Game Theory: an Introduction, by Tadelis. Since the exercises from later chapters are not available online, and since they represent some of the more creative and fun challenges, I just wanted to post a few exercises which I worked out, as well as some (unasked) variations.
Exercise 12.2: Cournot Revisited This exercise asks the following:
Consider the Cournot duopoly model in which two firms, 1 and 2, simultaneously choose the quantities they supply, \(q_1\) and \(q_2\).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Within (FE) Estimator Visualized</title>
      <link>/blog/2022-08-03-the-within-fe-estimator-visualized/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2022-08-03-the-within-fe-estimator-visualized/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this post, I will visualize what the FE-estimator does by benchmarking it to the OLS estimator. I use World Bank data on trade and GDP per capita to estimate (i) a regression equation with OLS, (ii) describing the procedure involved in estimating the FE coefficient and (iii) visualize what that means in this specific setting.
Downloading the Data First of all, we make use of the WDI package in R to download some (admittedly, pretty random) World Bank data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Solving for a Bayesian Perfect Equilibrium: A simple example</title>
      <link>/blog/2022-08-03-solving-for-a-bayesian-perfect-equilibrium-a-simple-example/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2022-08-03-solving-for-a-bayesian-perfect-equilibrium-a-simple-example/</guid>
      <description>Introduction I just want to set up a reminder on how to solve for Perfect Bayesian Equilibria (PBE) in the case there might be no pooling or separating equilibria, or in the case there might be additional equilibria next to pooling or separating equilibria. I will do this on the basis of a short game, which is depicted in the figure below, taken from this video. The game is about a &amp;ldquo;terrorist group&amp;rdquo; and a &amp;ldquo;state&amp;rdquo;, whose interests are, respectively, committing terrorist attacks and preventing/resisting them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working with git from R using usethis</title>
      <link>/blog/2022-08-03-working-with-git-from-r-using-usethis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2022-08-03-working-with-git-from-r-using-usethis/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This post serves as a reminder and introduction into the usethis package, which provides an interface (and sometimes, a guide) to efficiently working with git from within R. We suppose that git (a version control system) is already installed on your system. The workflow should not vary between operating systems.
Packages like blogdown or hugodown often allow the user to create a folder, with lots of auxilary and supplementary files and an appropriate structure to ensure things work as they&amp;rsquo;re supposed to.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Selenium in Python</title>
      <link>/blog/2022-08-02-selenium-in-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2022-08-02-selenium-in-python/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This is a small user guide to getting Selenium to work in Python (on a MacOS). In my experience, the Python-Selenium combo works a little bit more smoothly than the R variant. Python seems to be a little bit faster, but the real advantage comes from not having to use Docker: your system will just load a browser (which you can see), and then program, using a for loop, for instance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Automated Reading of Tables from PDF Documents</title>
      <link>/blog/2022-08-02-automated-reading-of-tables-from-pdf-documents/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2022-08-02-automated-reading-of-tables-from-pdf-documents/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this post, I will briefly explain how to read in a table easily from the Indonesian data sources that I have been planning to use (see here). First, I download the file, containing data about municipalities in every province and their GRDP:
if(!is.element(&amp;#34;hello.pdf&amp;#34;, list.files())){ download.file(&amp;#34;https://www.bps.go.id/publication/download.html?nrbvfeve=OTgxMmExYzRlYTI1Mjk4MDA0ODM5NTk2&amp;amp;xzmn=aHR0cHM6Ly93d3cuYnBzLmdvLmlkL3B1YmxpY2F0aW9uLzIwMTkvMTAvMDQvOTgxMmExYzRlYTI1Mjk4MDA0ODM5NTk2L3Byb2R1ay1kb21lc3Rpay1yZWdpb25hbC1icnV0by1rYWJ1cGF0ZW4ta290YS1kaS1pbmRvbmVzaWEtMjAxNC0yMDE4Lmh0bWw%3D&amp;amp;twoadfnoarfeauf=MjAyMi0wOC0wMyAwMDo1NDoyMg%3D%3D&amp;#34;, destfile = &amp;#34;hello.pdf&amp;#34;)} Reading in the table There are different ways in which I can read the table. First, I use the tabulizer package, from which I can use the extract_tables function, with two arguments:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Batch downloading with Selenium</title>
      <link>/blog/2022-08-02-batch-downloading-with-selenium/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2022-08-02-batch-downloading-with-selenium/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this blogpost, I briefly explain how to batch download files in RSelenium. This can be super useful if you want to download some pdf&amp;rsquo;s or other files, but you don&amp;rsquo;t want to click &amp;lsquo;download&amp;rsquo; a 1000 times, and there is no other option available.
Step 1: Setting up a Docker Container In this case, we have to deviate from the standard case of setting up a Docker container.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Webscraping with RSelenium</title>
      <link>/blog/2022-08-02-webscraping-with-rselenium/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2022-08-02-webscraping-with-rselenium/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this blogpost, I want to tell you about web scraping using RSelenium, something which I&amp;rsquo;ve recently been learning and which I am very enthusiastic about, because it is very powerful. I want to do this in the context of an example. I have been supervising undergraduate students, and a group of students asked me where they could get a list of members of the Iranian parliament. So I went to the official English-language website of the Iranian parliament, and looked up the list of members.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R vs. Excel: A quick comparison</title>
      <link>/blog/2022-08-02-r-vs-excel-a-quick-comparison/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2022-08-02-r-vs-excel-a-quick-comparison/</guid>
      <description>Once upon a time, I wrote a small pamphlet called ‘R vs. Excel: A quick comparison’ aimed at former or current Excel users to convince them to take up R, and leave aside Microsoft Excel entirely. I think the pamphlet contains some good arguments, so you can read about it here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making a website with blogdown</title>
      <link>/blog/2022-08-02-making-a-website-with-blogdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2022-08-02-making-a-website-with-blogdown/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This is the first blog post on my own website. I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to make this website using the R package blogdown. The website looks very nice now (in my humble opinion), but it was tedious to make. When attempting to create the website, I first tried out a couple of themes before I settled on the basic &amp;ldquo;lithium&amp;rdquo; theme, because it was by far the easiest theme to wrap your head around.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R: filtering with across in dplyr</title>
      <link>/blog/2022-08-02-r-filtering-with-across-in-dplyr/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2022-08-02-r-filtering-with-across-in-dplyr/</guid>
      <description>Introduction The newest versions of the dplyr package introduced a new function, across(), to be used within summarise, mutate and filter functions, and I am trying to learn it. I am, however, having a hard time understanding the use and the mechanics of the function in combination with filter. While this vignette has ample examples on mutate and summarise, the examples on filter are few and not very insightful. The same is true for several non-official guides that I have read.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Big Data, Big Questions</title>
      <link>/project/bdbq/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/bdbq/</guid>
      <description>Introduction The links above contain:
A repository for my course materials used in the working groups for the course Big Data, Big Questions at Utrecht University.
This includes data sources, lecture slides, and other resources The lecture slides</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2019 13:38:41 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/contact/</guid>
      <description>** Contact page don&amp;rsquo;t contain a body, just the front matter above. See form.html in the layouts folder.
Formspree requires a (free) account and new form to be set up. The link is made on the final published url in the field: Restrict to Domain. It is possible to register up to 2 emails free and you can select which one you want the forms to go to within Formspree in the Settings tab.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contributors</title>
      <link>/contributors/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/contributors/</guid>
      <description>Thank you to all the folks who have contributed both technical and creative skills to this project:
Desirée De Leon 🦒 (designed 5 of the custom color themes, made illustrations for the workshop, and provided general aesthetic feedback along the way)
Garrick Aden-Buie 🧙‍♀️ (debugged headroom.js and lent his panelset.js code to the theme)
Allison Horst 🐕 (awesome illustrations of campfires, seedlings, and evergreens, as well as my R Markdown hedgehog mascot 🦔)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>License</title>
      <link>/license/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/license/</guid>
      <description>My blog posts are released under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
