<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Articles on Bas Machielsen</title>
    <link>/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Articles on Bas Machielsen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Returns to Political Tenure</title>
      <link>/articles/polrents/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/articles/polrents/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Economists frequently assert that politicians derive financial returns from a political career, but these returns can be obscured by the varying duration of political careers. In this study, I estimate the financial returns associated with successive mandates in the Lower House, capitalizing on the repetitive treatment assignment through close elections in the Netherlands from 1848-1917. Employing a dynamic regression discontinuity framework, I establish that the financial benefits accruing to politicians exhibit a distinct &amp;ldquo;gate-keeping&amp;rdquo; pattern: no financial gains are observed during the first period of political tenure, but substantial returns emerge during the second term.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Democratization, Personal Wealth of Politicians and Voting Behavior</title>
      <link>/articles/polelite_vb/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/articles/polelite_vb/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Between about 1850 and 1920, Western Europe underwent a period of democratization and liberalization, resulting in the expansion of government and the establishment of universal suffrage. This paper examines the impact of politicians&amp;rsquo; personal wealth on this process, with a focus on the case of the Netherlands, using data from newly-collected probate inventories as a measure of politicians&amp;rsquo; wealth. The paper finds that the wealth of parliaments decreased significantly over time, and that richer politicians were more likely to vote against fiscal legislation, suggesting that personal wealth negatively influenced the probability of increasing taxes and played a role in determining government size.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD Thesis</title>
      <link>/articles/phd_thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/articles/phd_thesis/</guid>
      <description>My PhD Thesis My PhD Thesis is available in two parts. First, the actual thesis, which is downloadable via this link.
Replication Package The main thesis is accompanied by a replication package, which can be found here. The purpose of this package is to share shareable data, but also to make my findings reproducible by showing the code that lead to the results in each table.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Wealth of The Dutch Political Elite (1870-1922)</title>
      <link>/articles/wealth/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/articles/wealth/</guid>
      <description>Abstract Using newly-collected archival data, this study investigates the wealth and investment portfolio&amp;rsquo;s of Dutch politicians from 1870 to 1922. In a period when the political and economic situation underwent many changes, this study finds that the political arena remains rather static: politicians are wealthy in comparison to the average citizen. Secondly, Upper House members are by far the wealthiest politicians followed by executives. Lower house politicians are the poorest on average, consistent with the lower house being accessible by the entire male population of the country.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
